Guide to the Records of Office of the Chancellor RG.3.0.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Chancellor
1827-1890
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of the Chancellor
RG.3.0.1
7 Linear Feet 7.0 linear feet
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Reproduction of ALS, from T. Dwight to Thomas H. Gallaudet, dated: February 1, 1831. Located in Thomas H. Gallaudet biographical file. Reproduction courtesy of Kenneth S. Rothschild.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
This collection is organized as one series.
Scope and Content Note
The records include correspondence concerning the founding of the University with outlines of founding principles, reports on the different plans necessary for organization, subscription book and lists, charter and act of incorporation, council minutes, reports of the University Committees, address to the citizens of New York concerning the University's relationship to Columbia College, convention addresses, inaugural address of Chancellor James M. Mathews, invitations to meetings and conventions, bills and receipts, 1827-1831. Correspondents include John Delafield, Albert Gallatin, Thomas H. Gallaudet, Moran Lewis, Francis Lieber, James M. Mathews, Myndert Van Schaik, and Jonathan M. Wainwright.
Also included is material about the original University building at Washington Square constructed in 1835, with the deed of sale for Washington Square property, requests for work on the building, minutes of the Building Committee, estimates for construction, specifications and descriptions, laying of the cornerstone, and bills and receipts,1833-1836. Correspondents include John Delafield, Seth Geer, Valentine Mott, Dr W. B. Sprague, Samuel Thomson, and the architectural firm of Town, Davis & Dakin.
University financial records include subscription lists, loan and mortgage agreements, fire insurance policies, resolutions about a system of finance for the University, library fees, graduation fees, reports on scholarships, scholarship forms, lists of paying students, professorial endowments, professorial salaries, commencement expenses, bank book, reports and published statements of the Finance Committee, correspondence from the firm of Ward & Ogden concerning the rental of floors in University Building to merchants, estimates for renovations and alterations to University Building, Alumni endowment fund record, payment of salaries in funded coupons, and bills and receipts, 1830-1882.
In addition, the records contain the Chancellor's annual reports to the Council, reports to Regents of the University of the State of New York, committee reports, departmental reports, report of Committee on Elections, reports of honorary degrees, Council minutes, grade sheets, merit book, degrees granted with lists of recipients, resolutions by alumni, applications and testimonials about German professorships, newspaper articles about the University, and printed material issued by the University, 1830-1888.
Of particular interest in the records are the following: an original subscription book; a letter from Gallatin to Delafield (Jan. 10, 1831) expressing his views on the University; a letter from James Milnor discussing the "religious dimension" of the University (Feb. 10, 1835); Benjamin F. Butler and James M. Mathews correspondence concerning the founding of the law school in 1835; Charles Butler correspondence with Mathews from Albany concerning state propriation; letters from Samuel F. B. Morse complaining about conditions in University Building (Feb. and April, 1836); a report concerning the establishment of the Medical faculty (January 1837); letters and reports about the faculty controversy of 1838; tenants agreements for the University building (Oct. 1, 1849); a petition requesting the dismissal of Professor George Anthon (March 1851); rules of order and discipline, 1853; commencement costs for the class of 1854 (March 6, 1854); letter concerning Morse's telegraphic invention (Oct. 4, 1854); printed list of professors and instructors for 1857-1858; a plan for the reorganiztion of the Law School in 1858; an annotated catalog of the University for 1859-1860 from Chancellor Isaac Ferris' desk; letter from Regents regarding military organization during the Civil War (1862); class cards for the Medical School, 1864-1865; Benjamin Abbott's views on legal instruction at the University (Jul. 8, 1864); proposed course of Law study and reorganization of the Law faculty (Aug. 3, 1864); John W. Draper's report on the Medical School fire (May 25, 1866); a letter from George Comfort to Chancellor Ferris about scholarly societies (Jun. 1, 1868); a letter from John Draper to Howard Crosby about a meeting to discuss the reorganization of the University, July 22, 1870; a plan for the Departments of Science and Arts, June 22, 1871; lecture notices for free education programs, 1871-1872; correspondence with the Royal College of Surgeons, April and June 1876; and printed material of the Council, faculty, and administration pertaining to the "Crisis of 1881."
Additional correspondents include Henry Martyn Baird, Benjamin F. Butler, Charles Butler, Thomas Clarke, Howard Crosby, Henry E. Davies, Henry Draper, John W. Draper, Isaac Ferris, Theodore Frelinghuysen, Alfred H. Guernsey, John Hall, Joseph Henry, David R. Jaques, M. K. Jesup, John Taylor Johnston, Elias Loomis, Benjamin N. Martin, William R. Martin, Cyrus Mason, James McCosh, John Mulligan, William C. Noyes, James Parton, Noah Porter, Whitelaw Reid, T. Addison Richards, James Tallmadge, Henry P. Tappan, John Torrey, Henry Tuckerman, W. S. Tyler, and Henry Vethake.
Historical Note
This collection includes materials from the office of the chancellor, the highest administrative office at New York University at the time, dating from the founding of the unversity.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Bills.; Receipts (financial records).; vouchers.; Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1792-1854; Gallaudet, T. H. (Thomas Hopkins), 1787-1851; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844; Delafield, John; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849; Mott, Valentine, 1785-1865; Thomson, Samuel, 1769-1843; Lieber, Francis, 1800-1872; Mathews, J. M. (James McFarlane), 1785-1870
- Series I
  - Letters from the Reverend James M. Mathews, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Invitations to meeting to consider establishment of the University, 1830 Jan. 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Petition of the New University, 1830 Jan. 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Invitation to Meeting Re: Establishment of the University, 1830 Sept. 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report of Committee on the Plan of Organization for the University (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - An address to the citizens of New York on the claims of Columbia College and the New University to their patronage (reaction of Columbia College), 1830 Jan. 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reaction of Columbia College, 1830 Jan.-1830 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Funding of Columbia College, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Jonathan M. Wainwright's subscription book (note indicates: see Standing Committee minutes, Feb. 15, 1830), 1830 Jan. 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, John Delafield to Mathews; John Gibson to Mathews, Wainwright, and Delafield, 1830 July. 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter, John B. Gibson to Mathews, 1830 Sept. 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitations to Literary Convention of 1830, 1830 Sept. 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - William C. Woodbridge correspondence including responses to invitation to meet and other matters, 1831 Jan. 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thomas H. Gallaudet to mathews including response to invitation to mee and other matters., 1830 Sept. 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Henry E. Dwight to Delafield with response to invitation to meet and other matters, 1830 Sept. 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Samuel H. Turner to Mathews with response to invitation to meeting; Jared Sparks to Mathews, Wainwright and Delafield letters, Sept. 23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Albert Gallatin to Delafield concerning assistance, 1830 Sept. 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Benjamin Silliman to Mathews, response and other matters, 1830 Oct. 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - J. Irvine [?] to Mathews, Wainwright, Gallatin, and Delafield: response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - R. Emmett [?] to Delafield, declining an offer, 1830 Oct. 6 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Edward Robinson to Mathews, on printed notice of prospectus of Repository of Biblical Literature; response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 7 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nathaniel Chauncey to Mathews, Wainwright, and Delafield: response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 8 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Francis Leiber to Wainwright, Mathews, Gallatin, and Delafield: response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Edward Everett to Mathews, Wainwright, and Delafield: response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - F. R. Hassler response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Roger Sherman response with note on founding University, 1830 Oct. 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Printed list of subscribers, 1830 Oct. 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - List of subscribers as of Oct 13, 1830 (prepared by Dr. Jones), 1830 Oct. 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Typescript and manuscript lists of subscribers, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter, Wainwright to Delafield, 1830 Oct. 13 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Election of First Council, certified, 1830 Oct. 13-1830 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Council Minutes (handwritten), 1830 Oct 13-Dec (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter, Hon. T. Grimhe to Mathews, response to invitation, 1830 Oct. 14 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Henry Vethake to Mathews, 1830 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - I. Chaplin to Mathews, 1830 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Myndert Van Schaick to Delafield, response with note about the founding of the University, 1830 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Francis Lieber to John Delafield, 1830 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dr. Eliphalet Nott (Union College) to Mathews, 1830 Oct. 16 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Moses Stuart to Committee, 1830 Oct. 18 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Council Minutes of the first meeting of the Council of the University, 1830 Oct. 18 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Literary Convention replies, from those unable to attend (no significant comments), 1830 Oct. 20 (Box 1)
  - Jared Sparks to Delafield, about sketch of organization of Harvard College, 1830 Nov. 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Joseph Leo Wolf to Delafield, about account of German Universities, 1830 Nov. 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Francis Lieber to Delafield, his view as a foreigner to the convention, 1830 Nov. 3 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Gallatin to Delafield, about speaking at Convention, 1830 Nov. 8 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - William R. Keating to Delafield, about address at Convention, 1830 Nov. 15 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Roswell Park to John Delafield, 1830 Nov. 30 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Thomas H. Gallaudet to Delafield, 1830 Dec. 27 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Founding materials include: printed notice of particulars of principles on which the University was established, printed notice to fellow citizens on a more detailed exposition of the manner in which the founding principles were to be carried out; letter from Dr. Wainwright on learning seminary, Delafield's outline of the NYU program; letter from Horatio Gatso Spofford to editors at Courier and Enquirer; letter from Moran Lewis to Delafield and Van Schaick about money subscribed to the University; printed notice of statement of general principles upon which the Univeristy is to be established and with the conditions upon which patronage and subscriptions are to be solicited; and one letter to Delafield, and one from D.H. Mahon; printed "A Letter to the Editor of Courier and Enquirer in reply to that paper on the College Question.", 1830 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Report of a Committee on the Plan of Organization for the University of the City of New York (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letters, Watson Webb to Delafield about printing office; Mathews to Delafield, 1830? (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Receipts for capital stock, 1831 Jan. 3 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Gallatin to Delafield (presumably the earlier of two letters to Delafield written on the same day), 1831 Jan. 10 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Gallatin to Delafield (presumably the latter of two letters to Delafield written on the same day), photocopy (See: Box 14, folder 1 for original), 1831 Jan. 10 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Gallatin to Delafield, 1831 Jan. 12 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - An act incorporating the University of the City of New York, handwritten, amended and adopted on this date; an amendment to this act, 1831 Jan. 20 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Moran Lewis to New York State Legislature, original not dated (memorial was adopted at Council meeting on this date); Francis Lieber to Delafield, about receiving report of the Literary Convention (See: Box 14, folder 2), Jan. 28 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Charles L. Livingston to Delafield, 1831 Feb. 14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gallatin to Delafield, 1831 Feb. 16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - William Dunlap to Council, invitation to witness the mode of instruction in the Arts of Design in operation at the National Academy, 1831 Feb. 21 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letter, 1831 Mar. 7 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Charter and Statutes, Report of the Counci Committee on, 1831 Apr. 18 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Charter, Act of Incorporation, copy of the Incorporation of the University of the City of New York (See: Box 14, folder 3), 1831 Apr. 18 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Report on University organization, 1831 May. 24 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - William A. Colman to Gallatin, 1831 Jun. 17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resolutions adopted at meeting of Literary Convention, 1831 Sept. 13 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1831 Jun.-1831 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Literary Convention materials include: members invited, Council Minutes, communications about education in other institutions, and constitution of National Society of Science, Literature, and the Arts (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Report on expediency and advantages of establishing professorships of history in universities, 1831 Nov. 5 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Same report as above in handwritten and typescript done by Jared Sparks, William C. Woodbridge, and Francis Lieber, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - University to William H. Buckley, possibly bill for legall services (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters about real estate at Washington Square and other matters (some correspondence in French), 1832 Jan -1832 Jun (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1832 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Report of the Council Committee on Measures to open the University in October 1832, 1832 Apr. 19 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Report of the Council Committee on the subject establishing of a professorship of Law, 1832 May. 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dr. James Milnor's address at the opening of the University, 1832 Sept. 26 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Inaugural address of Chancellor James M. Mathews, handwritten original and printed copy as it appeared in his Recollections of Persons and Events chiefly in the City of New York being selections from his Journals (NY: Sheldon & Co., 1865) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Extracts from letters of George W. Strong to his brother-in-law, John Nelson Lloyd, with reference to the University (typescript copies), 1832 Oct. 9 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Deed of sale of Washington Square property, Samuel Thomson to University; with preceding transactions, 1832 Nov. 26 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Requests for work on University Building, 1832-1840 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Valentine Mott to John Delafield, 1832?-1838? (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Bill, Samuel Thomson re sale of Washington Square property, 1833 Mar. 15 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letter to Dr. Otis Pollard, 1833 Apr. 7 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Stonework for original building contract between Robert Willse (?) agent and University; contract and prices for University building, 1833 Apr. 24 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Estimates for construction of original building, 1833 May. 9 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence from Dr. [?] Sprague, 1833 May. 18 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ithiel [?] Town, building estimate; Copy of survey site for University Building (See: Box 14, folder 4) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Specifications and description of original building (printed copy) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Articles of agreement between University and builder Seth Geer; also correspondence and carpenter's estimate (See also: Box 14, folder 5), 1833 May. 13 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Construction bills for University building from Seth Geer, 1833 June -1836 May (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Letter about the laying of the cornerstone and aims of the University, 1833 Jul. 16 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Comment of founding of University (NY Mirror, Aug. 31, 1833 [?]), 1833 Aug. 31 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Sun, 1833 Sept. 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Chancellor's Report, 1833 Oct. 23 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letter from Vethake, Milligan, and Torrey to Council and salaries (See: Box 14, folder 6), 1833 Nov 4-Nov 5 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Anonymous letter about University and about Chancellor Mathews, 1833 Nov. 15 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Photocopy of bills from the architectural firm of Town, Davis & Dakin, 1833 Nov-1834 Jul (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - An Exposition of the Reasons for the Resignation of Some of the Professors in the University of the City of New York (printed), 1833 Nov. 21 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence about the controversty between the Chancellor and the faculty (Nov.); Report of the Council Election; correspondence from Mathews, 1833 Nov. 4 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence with Seth Geer about University Building bills; Minute boo of the Building Committee (See Box 13, folder 1), 1833-1836 1833-1838 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence with Mathews about fees for the University; Report of the Committee of Advice (Feb. 4-April 1834); Communications from the Committee to promote the formation of a Central Seminary (Feb. 1, 1834); Report of the Building Committee (April 8, 1834); Internal Regulations of the University (Oct. 1834); letter from William Gaston, 1834 Jan. -1834 Oct. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Salisbury loan and mortgage; Report of Building Committee; Salisbury loan and mortgage (See: Box 14, folder 7), 1834 Feb.-1834 Jun. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baccalaureate address at University Commencement of 1834, by James M. Mathews, (original, transcript, and digest), 1834 Jul. 17 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Building Committee letters to Seth Geer, 1834 Nov. 8 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Professor of Ancient Classical Languages (July 15) in Chancellor's Report, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bills and vouchers, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence of James Milnor about the religious dimension of the University, its non-sectarianism Journal of Commerce (See: Box 14, folder 8), 1835 Feb. 10 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from Abby Salisbury, of University, about court case, 1835 May. 30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper report of the meeting of the Council concerning the Law faculty, 1835 Jun. 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Third annual commencement notes; Newspaper article about commencement (See: Box 14, folder 9) New York Daily Advertiser article about commencement (See: Box 14, folder 10), Jul 16-18, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Winham contract, agreement for original building, 1835 Oct. 9 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Organization of the Law Association, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence with Mathews, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bill, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Building Committee, surveying structure Samuel F. B. Morse, letter about conditions in University Building (See: Box 14, fldr. 11) Trustees to Samuel F. B. Morse, letter about damages to Morse's property (See: Box 14, fldr. 12) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Samuel F.B. Morse, letter to Chancellor about conditions in University Building, 1835 Apr. 30 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Agreement with builder about University Chapel; specifications of carpenter's work and platerer's work, 1836 Jun. 14 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Arbitration bond between Seth Geer and University; arbitration bond and satisfaction with the university, 1836 Aug. 24 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Specification for painting the central compartment of the ceiling in the university chapel, 1836 Dec. 8 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence from superintendent to the Building Committee about the roof; correspondence about increase in salary and a library for the University; also annual course of instruction; council notice of election, 1836 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bills and vouchers (See also: Box 14, folder 13), 1836 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Agreement to delay payment to Seth Geer, 1836 [?] (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Letter, Chancellor Mathews to New York State Legislature about establishing a Medical faculty at the University; Fire insurance policies (See: Box 14, folder 14), 1837 Jan. 7 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Subscription for mineral cabinet (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Boston Weekly Messenger clippings about the dedication of University building, 1837 Jun. 8 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Plan of university building, 1837 Jun. 10 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper clipping about commencement, 1837 Jul. 20 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Certificate of honorary membership to the Philomathean Society; also invitation to anniversary, 1837 Dec. 6 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Legislation about contract for stonework, 1837 Dec 13-1838 Dec 5 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence and reports including: Resolution about the Library, Feb.25; instructions to examine Dr. Milnor; Report of the President; Report on Organization of Sacred Literature; letter, Aug. 7, about the grammar school; Report of the Faculty to the Committee of Finance of Council to NYU; Report of Committee about the Medical Faculty; letter, Dec. 13, from William A. Norton; bills, May 26, for Building; letter, Aug. 18, about rental of rooms for Classical school, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Bills and vouchers, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Plan for Medical Faculty, report on organization, and plan as adopted, 1838 Jan. 10 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Letter, Benjamin F. Butler to J. Tallmadge, 1838 Feb. 9 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Mathews to C. Butler about legislation, 1823 Feb 9-1838 Mar (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bills receivable and payable, 1838 Mar. 22 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Photocopy of Samuel F.B. Morse F.O.J. Smith, 1838 Apr. 13 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Plan for Oriental languages, 1838 May. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Senior Class accounts (treasury) (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Report to Regents for year ending August 1838, 1838 Aug. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Subscriptions to NYU, 1838 Sept. 11 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Student petitions concerning the Controversy of 1838, 1838 Sept. 19 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Report of Committee of Council on Controversy of 1838, 1838 Sept. 27 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Letter, Benjamin Butler to Charles Butler, about political views and University "warfare", 1838 Oct. 4 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Exposition for Council, on Controversy of 1838 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Manuscript copy of appendix to History of the Controversy, partly by William C. Noyes [?], 1838 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 45)